Guide to the Paul Bartsch papers, 1894-1945 MS0250.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Paul Bartsch papers
1894-1945
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Bartsch, Paul
MS0250.UA
0.5 Linear Feet
Paul Bartsch (1871-1960) taught biological science and zoology at The George Washington University (GW) from 1899 to 1939 and became a professor emeritus in 1937 through 1960. He was a zoologist who specialized in mollusks. Bartsch held many important positions throughout his life including, professor emeritus at GW and curator of the mollusks division of the US National Museum. Collection consists of papers, a scrapbook, and pilot charts of waters. They range in date from 1894 to 1945 and their provenance is unknown. The old accession log listed it as being received in 1987.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Provenance of this collection is unknown.
Historical or Biographical Note
Paul Bartsch (1871-1960) taught biological science and zoology at The George Washington University (GW) from 1899 to 1939 and became a professor emeritus in 1937 through 1960. He was a zoologist who specialized in mollusks. Bartsch held many important positions throughout his life including, professor emeritus at GW and curator of the mollusks division of the US National Museum.
Paul Bartsch was born in Silesia, Germany (currently Poland) in 1871. The Bartsch family immigrated to the United States in the 1880s, and settled down in Burlington, Iowa. Paul enrolled in sciences classes at the State University of Iowa; however, before completing his degree he left Iowa to work under William H. Dall, the honorary curator of the Division of Mollusks at the United States National Museum in Washington, DC. In 1914, Bartsch became the curator of the Division of Mollusks. His work at the Smithsonian led to many expeditions including those to the Philippines, Cuba, and the West Indies. He retired from his Smithsonian position in 1946.
While at the Smithsonian, Bartsch continued his research work on mollusks in addition to teaching biology, zoology, and histology to university students. Bartsch taught histology in the medical school at Howard University and eventually became director of the Histological and Physiological laboratory, a position that lasted thirty-seven years. Furthermore, he started teaching science and zoology at the GW in 1899 and became Professor emeritus in 1937. Bartsch continued as Professor emeritus at GW until 1960.
In addition to receiving a Ph.D. from the University of Iowa (1905), Bartsch also received an honorary Doctor of Science degree from GW in 1937.
Bartsch was also the president of numerous societies, including the Wild Flower Preservation Society (1920-1924), the Biological Society in Washington D.C. (1913-1915), and Vice President of the Washington Academy (1913-1915).
Bartsch died in 1960.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
This collection consists of papers, a scrapbook, and pilot charts of waters. They range in date from 1894 to 1945 and their provenance is unknown. The old accession log listed it as being received in 1987.
The Smithsonian Institution Archives holds other papers of Paul Bartsch.
Scrapbooks; Nautical charts; Ornithology; Zoology; Washington (D.C.); George Washington University
- Patent applications for "Wood Protection" (photocopies), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Ornithology class lists and charts of field trip observations, 1935 - 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Ornithology class lists and charts of field trip observations (continued):, 1935 - 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Please note the bird watching records for Margaret Sheer (Summer 1935) and Helen K. Hoyem (June 1938) are on loan to the Smithsonian Anacostia Community Museum. These items will be returned October 2013.
- Miscellaneous contents: notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  General note
  Notes on evolution; vacation correspondence; essay on Theodore Sherman Palmer; memo from Board of Engineers for Rivers and Harbors re: Potomac River Survey, 1945; Farragut Square and C&O Canal pamphlets published by US Department of the Interior; anonymous poem; lecture to Audubon Society; address by Bartsch at Opening of the Corcoran Scientific School, Sept. 24, 1902.
- Pilot Charts of the Central American Waters: (4 charts), 08/1929 - 12/1929 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Pilot Charts of the North Atlantic Ocean: (3 charts), 08/1929 - 12/1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Pilot Charts of the Upper Air, North Atlantic Ocean, (2 charts), 10/1929 - 12/1929 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Pilot Charts of the North Pacific Ocean, (5 charts), 09/1929 - 01/1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Pilot Charts of the Upper Air, North Pacific Ocean, (2 charts), 11/1929 - 01/1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Scrap book of 5 plant specimens, no written descriptions., undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Book entitled "Forty Years Notes of a Field Ornithologist", by John Krider, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Gift to Bartsch from Charles J. Pennock (inscription attached)
- Ornithology Record Book, 02/27/1894 - 04/05/1896 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Please note that this folder is on loan to the Smithsonian Anacostia Community Museum for an exhibit. It will be returned October 2013.
  Brief descriptions of bird sightings, Approximately 200 pages; in fragile condition.